John Ruskin: Letters to Thomas Goff Lupton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
John Ruskin: Letters to Thomas Goff Lupton
1845-1873
MSS.5
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
0.42
1 box
This collection comprises letters sent by John Ruskin to Thomas Goff Lupton (or his family) from 1850 to 1873. It also includes one ALS to Lupton from Benjamin Haydon, sent in 1845.
Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1786-1846
Biographical / Historical
John Ruskin was born on February 8, 1819, in London to John James Ruskin, a vintner, and his wife (and first cousin), Margaret Cox. A highly intelligent and creative child, Ruskin was already writing and drawing at an early age. An anecdote about a fictional piece written at the age of seven reveals much about the traits that marked Ruskin's later approach to his work: "The [seven year old Ruskin]...wished to control all aspects of book production: plates, print styles, title-page, and so on are all given detailed attention" (Batchelor, 17).
Anxious about his health and his social surroundings, John James and Margaret Ruskin kept their son, who was their only child, largely out of school and had him tutored at home. He received education in typical academic subjects, but was also given art lessons in childhood and youth. Although his parents eventually enrolled him in school when he was fourteen, Ruskin was soon pulled out of this formalized education in order to allow him to travel to Europe with them. As a teenager, Ruskin was still closely watched over by and spent most of his time with his mother and father. He seems to have had few friends his age, although he developed a passionate infatuation with the daughter of one of John James Ruskin's business partners. This romantic attachment was not fully mutual, and a matter of concern for Ruskin's parents, who ultimately did not want their son to marry a Catholic.
Determined to give their son the best education possible and to see him progress upwards in society, the Ruskins sent John to Oxford in January of 1837. In a move that would have been unusual in any other family, Mrs. Ruskin accompanied her son to college, finding lodgings separate from those of her son, but sharing most of her meals with him and keeping a watchful eye on his academic and social activities. Ruskin found a measure of social and intellectual camraderie with his fellow students at Oxford, although he was something of an odd man out, already being a published poet and critic at this time, and not possessed of a rambunctious temperament like many of his peers. When Ruskin suffered a lung hemorhrage in 1840, his parents withdrew him from the university and the family embarked on European travels meant to help Ruskin recuperate. He would eventually earn his degree in 1842.
It was after his years at Oxford that two very important and very different developments occurred in Ruskin's life. For one, he began the work that would eventually become his famous multi-volume Modern Painters. Inspired by J.M.W. Turner's art, and seeking to defend the painter against his critics, Ruskin's work took a philosophical and art historical approach to painting in general and, especially in the first volume, to Turner in particular. It was also around this time that Ruskin first met Effie Gray, who would eventually become his wife in April, 1848. The marriage was to last six years, during which time Ruskin published The Stones of Venice, a work about Venetian architecture. When J.M.W. Turner died in 1851, Ruskin hoped, as one of the painter's executors, to be involved in planning an exhibition hall at the National Gallery for Turner's works. This project did not materialize, and Ruskin ultimately seems to have devoted much of his energies in the 1850s into getting many of Turner's works into print, an enterprise that would involve his collaboration with Thomas Lupton.
In 1854, Effie left her husband, and the dissolution of their marriage (on the grounds of non-consummation) was to send Ruskin's personal life and public image into turmoil. Despite this crisis, Ruskin's professional productivity does not seem to have been deeply affected during the 1850s. Throughout this decade, Ruskin was involved with the completion of Modern Painters, the publication of The Harbours of England (a collection of engravings after Turner's works), and the organization of thousands of Turner items at the National Gallery. His letters to Thomas Lupton, the engraver with whom he would collaborate for The Harbours of England and on some of his books, make clear his dedication to his various projects and his insistence on their perfection.
In the 1860s and 1870s, Ruskin continued his rather heavy pace of work, turning some of his thinking to social issues outside of art. In these years he experienced crises in his psychological health (mental illness ran in his family) which often accompanied the waxing and waning of his relationship with Rose La Touche, a young woman with whom Ruskin had fallen in love while she was still a child, and whom he hoped eventually to marry. Ruskin's proposals were deferred and ultimately rejected, with his past failed marriage to Effie coming back to haunt him in the form of fears and doubts on the part of Rose's parents. When Rose La Touche eventually died in 1875, Ruskin was grief-stricken.
Despite his continuing personal crises, Ruskin's professional life made steady progress in the mid to late Victorian years, with a Slade Professorship being awarded to him in 1869. In the 1880s, Ruskin's mental health began to decline more seriously, however, and he retired somewhat from public life, working on autobiographical writings in addition to works on contemporary social issues. Despite his frailties and the publicity of some of his major personal problems, Ruskin's works established him as a well-respected art critic and political thinker, making him one of Victorian England's most valued minds. By the time of his death in 1900, his contributions ranged across many fields and influenced those in public service, in the arts, and in educational spheres.
Thomas Lupton: Thomas Goff Lupton was born in 1791 and apprenticed to engraver and painter George Clint in 1805. Lupton's portrait drawings were exhibited at the Royal Academy between 1811 and 1820. After his apprenticeship with Clint, Lupton went on to engrave pieces for J.M.W. Turner, beginning a close working relationship and friendship. Lupton married his wife Susannah on May 30, 1818. They had six sons and one daughter; their son Nevil would help his father with his engraving business and went on to become an admired landscape painter, winning the Royal Academy's Turner Medal in 1857. According to the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Lupton was instrumental in the introduction of "steel plates for engraving," in place of traditional copperplate.
Some of Lupton's most significant engravings date from the 1830s and 1840s, the decades marking the peak of his career. As DNB records, "[h]is finest single plates include Wellington Surveying the Field of Waterloo after Benjamin Robert Haydon (1841; original painting, 1839, NPG); Lord Byron after Thomas Phillips (1824; original painting, 1814, Gov. Art Coll., British embassy, Athens); and The Eddystone Lighthouse (1824; original watercolour untraced) and Sunrise, Whiting Fishing at Margate (1825; original watercolour untraced) after Turner."
Lupton collaborated with John Ruskin on a number of works, including The Harbours of England, which was a reworking of the 1826 Ports of England on which Lupton had collaborated directly with Turner. Lupton would also make engravings for parts of Ruskin's Modern Painters, among other works of the 1850s. Their friendship would continue until Lupton's death in 1873.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: I. Dated letters. II. Undated letters. The second series contains letters whose date could not be approximated to closer than one or two years. The single letter to Lupton from Benjamin Robert Haydon is the first item in series one.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Paul Mellon Collection.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises one letter from Benjamin Haydon and sixty-five letters from John Ruskin to Thomas Lupton and/or his son Nevil. Haydon's letter is a brief one in an angry tone, and seems to be related to some sort of professional falling out with Lupton. The scope of Ruskin's letters is far wider, and spans the professional and the personal. For the most part, John Ruskin appears to have been in close communication with Lupton about the engraving and printing of images for his books during the 1850s. In particular, the two men's connection to J.M.W. Turner, who had died in 1851, prompted their collaboration on works that sought to bring Turner's landscapes and other art into print. In addition to The Harbours of England, which featured Turner's engravings accompanied by an introductory essay by Ruskin, the correspondence covers such works as the third through final volumes of Ruskin's Modern Painters. Lupton, along with other engravers, was responsible for helping Ruskin to create many of the illustrations for these publications. It seems that Ruskin's commitment to Turner's legacy drove his rather furious pace of work and publications in the 1850s, the decade during which his personal life was most in turmoil. He remarks, in a New Year's message to Lupton in 1855, that he hopes the year will be a good one and that, "God willing--we will make it a busy one."
Ruskin's letters to Lupton reveal a very close working relationship, with both men working on plates at different stages, and sending plates and proofs back and forth to one another. Ruskin is anxious for perfection throughout, and frequently chides Lupton for delays or for departures from his instructions, despite the engraver's experience and well-established reputation at this time. Many of the letters relate specific directions about the handling of plates, and seem to have originally accompanied the plates themselves, carried to Lupton by one of Ruskin's servants. Ruskin's letters often express frustration with the other engravers involved in his projects, and he bemoans his difficult interactions with them to Lupton.
While the bulk of the correspondence dates from the 1850s, the years in which Ruskin and Lupton were most actively working together, it carries on throughout the 1860s and 1870s, until Lupton's death in 1873. Although Ruskin can be harsh, demanding, and impatient with Lupton in his professional correspondence, he seems able to offer genuinely friendly concern and communication at other times. For instance, Ruskin offers Lupton a moving letter of sympathy upon the death of the engraver's wife, Susannah, in 1864. Another letter of condolence, written to Lupton's son after Lupton died in 1873 (and in another person's handwriting), expresses the deep respect and affection that Ruskin held for his collaborator and friend. When Ruskin is in poor health (he suffered mental and physical illness especially during the 1860s and 1870s), he is relatively honest about his condition, informing Lupton of the reasons for gaps in his correspondence when he chooses to retire from work and communication in order to rest from time to time.
In addition to the correspondence with Thomas Goff Lupton, Ruskin writes a couple of letters to Lupton's son Nevil, who seems to have assisted his father both in the physical labor of his engravings and in the management of his business. Ruskin is respectful and kind in his messages to Nevil, and acknowledges his contributions.
Overall, the Lupton correspondence offers insight into the working relationship and friendship forged between John Ruskin and Thomas Lupton over two decades, during some of the most productive years of Ruskin's life and at a time when both men were contributing their skills to securing J.M.W. Turner's legacy, even as their own legacies were still being created. It illuminates the lengthy and painstaking process of creating each of the illustrations on which Lupton and Ruskin worked, and sheds light on Ruskin's professional style--impatient, industrious, efficient, and exacting.
Bibliography
Batchelor, John. No Wealth but Life. London: Chatto and Windus, 2000.
The Letters of John Ruskin to Lord and Lady Mount-Temple. John Bradley, Ed. Columbus, OH: Ohio State University Press, 1964.
Luytens, Mary. The Ruskins and the Grays. London: John Murray, 1972.
Luytens, Mary. Millais and the Ruskins. London: John Murray, 1967.
Bibliography
Piozzi, Hester Lynch. The Piozzi letters: correspondence of Hester Lynch Piozzi, 1784-1821 (formerly Mrs. Thrale), edited by Edward A. Bloom and Lillian D. Bloom. Newark: University of Delaware Press, c1989-1993.
Artists -- Great Britain -- Correspondence; Engravers -- Great Britain -- Correspondence; Engraving -- 19th century -- Great Britain; Etchers -- Great Britain -- Correspondence; Etching -- 19th century -- Great Britain; Illustration of books -- 19th century -- Great Britain; Mezzotint engraving -- 19th century -- Great Britain; Letters; Boys, Thomas Shotter, 1803-1874; Gambart, Ernest, 1814-1902; Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1786-1846 -- Correspondence; Lupton, Nevil Oliver, ca. 1830-1915 -- Correspondence; Lupton, Thomas Goff, 1791-1873 -- Correspondence; Lupton, Thomas, 1821-1910 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Friends and associates; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 ( Harbours of England); Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 ( Modern painters); Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851
- Dated letters, Series I
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1845; Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1786-1846; 3 p. (1 folded leaf + 1 separate leaf); 19 x 24 cm., 9 x 11 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Haydon writes a rather angry letter to Lupton, complaining about a delay from Lupton on a particular project (unspecified). Haydon accuses Lupton of not caring about him, and says that "after your experience & what I have suffered I really do not think it kind of you to delay it in such a manner." Oddly, and perhaps at random, an autograph that may be William Wordsworth's, on a separate sheet, was preserved with this letter. A blue envelope is labeled "Letter from B.R. Haydon with Wordsworth's autograph."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1850 August 27; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 16 x 20 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sent from Herne Hill, Dulwich and addressed to Lupton at Burchetts, in Sussex. The letter appears to be one of the first between Ruskin and Lupton. The tone is politely distant and the content suggests that Ruskin had not worked with Lupton before. Ruskin inquires about the possibility of Lupton making an engraving for the Arundel Society, an art appreciation group that he had helped to found in 1849. Ruskin describes the piece as involving figures, "logs of woods, baskets, vegetables, and such stuff," and being about "three feet by two feet" in size. He asks for details on the process and time required, and says that he would like to present information to the Arundel Council soon. Envelope contains a note stating "wishes gunpowder had never been invented."
    Arundel Society for Promoting the Knowledge of Art
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, circa 1851; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Addressed to Lupton at 4 Keppel Street, Russell Square. Ruskin asks about the pattern of letters engraved, saying that the letters are "bigger by a third than any in the book." He asks Lupton to correct them "as now pencilled above" and "speedily." Says that he has written to Brooke to lend Lupton more plates. He comments that the "retouchings [are] all right," and directs Lupton to "look at the Book--vol III" for a pattern for the title of "stones." This likely refers to The Stones of Venice, the first work on which Ruskin and Lupton collaborated.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 January 1; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 leaf); 14 x 9 cm. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Ruskin writes to wish Lupton a happy new year. He comments, "God willing we will make it a busy one." He asks if Lupton will be at home to receive his plate and arrange biting for it. He says that he will leave directions with his servant to take it to a Mr. Armytage if Lupton is out of town.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1855?] February 7; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letter and envelope dated "Feb 7." Ruskin writes to Lupton of his dismay at the "quantity of trouble I find necessary in making the drawing on the etching..." He complains that he has not been able to finish the bottom of the drawing, but sends it anyway for Lupton's work. Ruskin remarks that he will soon have the "St. Gothard" (an image printed in the third volume of Modern Painters) ready soon. He refers to three etchings, presumably carried to Lupton (the envelope bears no postal stamps). He gives Lupton specific directions and tips about the three pieces. He includes a rough sketch to show Lupton a particular portion of the last etching that he wants him to leave until later. Ruskin acknowledges that Lupton's son "has been very kind & speedy in fulfilling all my wishes," and sends his best regards to him. He closes with a wish that Lupton has enjoyed himself and a note that he will send the "St. Gothard" for grounding on the following Tuesday.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 March 27; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A brief note addressed to Lupton at Russell Square, sent from Denmark Hill. Ruskin writes that he "forgot to say to send me 4 impressions from the plate of Bolton before regrounding it." He also reminds Lupton not to "bite too deep as there is delicate work on the round tops of crags & I will bite deeper afterwards when I want."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 April 7; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    A brief message in a rather buoyant tone. Ruskin writes Lupton to tell him that "all's right," however he has forgotten the proofs and does not have time for them on this day. He declares, "I have been going larking, like you, and not minding any of my business." Ruskin promises that he will be back to work and dealing with the proofs the next day.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1855?] May 21; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Sent from the Calverley Hotel in Tunbridge Wells, to Lupton at Russell Square. Envelope includes a note to say that the letter "may be opened by Mr. Nevil Lupton." Ruskin writes that he is finishing the text for the "marine plates of yours." He asks for the "particulars of [Lupton's]...intercourse with Turner reflecting them--as far as you are willing it should be made public." He asks for other details about the origin of the work, and inquires about a series of proofs that Lupton had sent him a year and a half before, asking whether they are "proofs from the plates in their present state." Ruskin seems anxious to get Lupton's answers, saying that an "early reply to above address will greatly oblige me."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 May 29; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 4 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    A dual letter, first sent from Ruskin to Lupton, and then apparently forwarded to Lupton by his son, Thomas Jr., with a note from the younger Lupton to his father written on the other side of Ruskin's letter. Ruskin asks about Lupton's health, and remarks that he too has been suffering from poor health in recent months. He asks if Lupton himself planned the work on Turner or Ackermann. He asks "who chose Tidmouth as one of the ports of England?" He asks further questions about the extent of Lupton's previous involvement with the Turner work.
    Thomas Lupton Jr. writes a letter to his father from their home in Russell Square, calling his attention to Ruskin's letter on the other side of the leaf. He also alerts him to other work concerns that have come up in the time that Lupton has been away, although noting that he hopes that Lupton is enjoying his visit to "the country" and that his heatlh is improving. He asks his father to stay there until the doctor declares him well. Lupton Jr. also provides other details about life at home, describing the weather and remarking that his mother is well. He includes Ruskin's address in Tunbridge Wells.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 October 6; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. Previously housed with ALS dated 15 October 1855 (Box 1, Folder 12). (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Letter addressed to Lupton at "Bouchetts, Wisborough, Sussex." Ruskin writes that he is "delighted by the contents of your note." He comments that he "can't think what Boys is about," and that a drawing is ready. He says that he will send it to Keppel Street (Lupton's home address) when he gets the etching.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 October 9; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes in an impatient tone, saying that he doesn't understand what "[Brooke/Boys] is about. I could have done it myself in half a day." He declares that he must pitch in his own efforts, "for this will never do." He refers to a plate (presumably sent with or around the same time as the letter) that he describes as badly begun, and asks Lupton to lay a new ground on it and to make tracing on it from an enclosed etching. He says, "I would make the tracing myself--but I don't know what pencil & paper are best..." He asks Lupton to send him the plate in a "deal box which can be made to carry two plates at a time without touching faces quite safely." Ruskin remarks about the plate: "In engraving the drawing, put as much work as you think proper on glacier and clouds & distant mountains on the main dark hill..." He specifies his desire for Lupton to make the engraving incorporate all of his "little touches." Ruskin closes with a request for Lupton to send him an expense account.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 October 15; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. Previously housed with ALS and envelope dated 6 October 1855 (Box 1, Folder 10). (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Lupton or someone else has noted on the reverse of the letter: "Mr Ruskin/ Monday Oct'r 15 55." Ruskin writes to Lupton asking if he could have a particular plate bitten "lightly but decisively all over..." He gives specific instructions to Lupton about the handling of this plate, advising him to use a magnifying glass to aid in the biting process. He notes that he has left a "cheque for 10" with Lupton's daughter, and asks for an expense account from the engraver. He asks, impatiently, for Lupton to send him the plate "as soon as my be."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 October 22; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 13)